Malintha Fernando

Ph.D. Candidate

Luddy School of Informatics, Computing and Engineering Indiana University
Bloomington, Indiana, USA, 47401
+1 (812) 955-8882

Research Overview

Toward Scalable, Cooperative Fleet Autonomy: With the dawn of *autonomous mobility*, and *Beyond 5G* networks there is a growing demand for coordinating *connected*, *mobile* robot fleets in stochastic environments. My research aims to answer the question: how to develop *heterogeneous* robot fleet autonomy to achieve *application-specific* group objectives in a *cooperative* and *scalable* manner? I study game theory, graph neural networks and deep multi-agent reinforcement learning to develop fleet autonomy along these dimensions with focus on low-level dynamics.

Education -

Indiana University, Bloomington

Ph.D. in Intelligent Systems Engineering

Email: ccfernan@iu.edu Website: malintha.site

Fall 2017 - Spring 2023

Fall 2021

2011 - 2015

Mentor: Tully Foote

Github: github.com/malintha

M.S. in Intelligent Systems Engineering **Supervised by**: Prof. Martin Swany

Major: Computer Engineering

Minor: Mathematics

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

B.Sc.(Hons.) in Information Technology December 2015

Royal College, Sri Lanka 2002 - 2010

GCE Advanced Level (Physical Sciences)2010 (Top 5% Nationwide)GCE Ordinary Level2007 (10 out of 10 % Passes)

Work Experiences

Open Robotics

Mountain View, California

Summer 2019

Software Engineer Intern

Contributions: Designed a framework for UAV swarm control supporting trajectory optimization and receding horizon planning (RHP).

Technologies: Robot Operating System (ROS), PX4, IBM CPLEX, C++, MATLAB.

WSO₂ 2014, 2016 - 2017

Colombo, Sri Lanka

Software EngineerJanuary 2016 - July 2017Software Engineer InternJanuary - June 2014

Contributions: Enhanced the integration of WSO₂ frameworks with client APIs, web services, and IOT devices.

Technologies: Java, Web Services, Web Security.

Other Technologies: Python, PyTorch, Ray Reinforcement Learning Library (RLLib), Deep Graph Library (DGL).

Teaching –

Indiana University

Associate Instructor

ENGR-533: Deep Learning Systems

Fall 2022

ENGR-210: Cyber-Physical Systems

Spring 2022, 2023

ENGR-321: Advanced Cyber-Physical Systems

Fall 2021

Co-conducted lectures, designed lecture materials, assignments on linear dynamical systems simulation and control*.

ENGR-210: Cyber-Physical Systems	Spring 2021
ENGR-523: Internet of Things	Spring 2019
ENGR-511: Machine Learning and Signal Processing	Fall 2018
ENGR-599: Autonomous Robotics	Fall 2017

^{*} Course materials: Github Link.

Publications -

Malintha Fernando, Ransalu Senanayake, Heeyoul Choi, Martin Swany, "Graph Attention Multi-Agent Fleet Autonomy for Advanced Air Mobility", *Under Review.* [Preprint]

Malintha Fernando, Ransalu Senanayake, Ariful Azad, Martin Swany, "Graphical Games for UAV Swarm Control Under Time-Varying Communication Networks", Intelligent Aerial Robotics: From Autonomous Micro Aerial Vehicles to Sustainable Urban Air Mobility and Operations, ICRA 2022.

Malintha Fernando, Ransalu Senanayake, Martin Swany, "CoCo Games: Graphical Game-Theoretic Swarm Control for Communication-Aware Coverage.", *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L), March, 2022*, [Paper][Video][Project Webpage]

Malintha Fernando "Online Flocking Control of UAVs with Mean-Field Approximation.", *International Conference on Robotics and Automation, (ICRA), Xi'an, China, 2021*, [Paper][Video][Code]

Z. Chen, **M. Fernando** and L. Liu, "A Visual Feature based Obstacle Avoidance Method for Autonomous Navigation," *IEEE Applied Imagery Pattern Recognition Workshop*, 2019.

Malintha Fernando, and Lantao Liu. "Formation Control and Navigation of a Quadrotor Swarm." *International Conference on Unmanned Aircraft Systems (ICUAS)*, *Atlanta, Georgia, 2019*. [Video]

Malintha Fernando, and Lantao Liu. "Swarming of Aerial Robots with Markov Random Field Optimization", 2020, [arXiv.]

Fernando Malintha, Cooray A.V.S, Indeewara T.G.H, Fernando S., "Semi-supervised Learning Framework for Knowledge Extraction in Cricket Domain", *ITRU research symposium (2015)*, *University of Moratuwa*, *Sri Lanka*.

Open Source Contributions –

MavSwarm

A Lightweight, ROS-based UAV swarm simulator with low-level control, trajectory optimization, and RHP [70+ Stars on Github].

ROSNS3

A *Network Simulator* (NS-3) bridge for ROS to simulate wireless communication aspects of *Primary Contributor* networked robot systems [Github Link].

Contributed by bug fixes and feature improvements to the browser core.

Talks -

IEEE International Conference on Robot & Human Interactive Communication (RO-MAN), August 2022

Invited Talk at University of Sydney - 2022 June

Workshop for Intelligent Aerial Robotics: From Autonomous Micro Aerial Vehicles to Sustainable Urban Air Mobility and Operations, ICRA 2022.

Guest Lecture on "UAV Swarm Simulation and Control", ENGR-321, Indiana University, 2021.

"Online Flocking Control of UAVs with Mean-Field Approximation" ICRA 2021 [Video].

Invited talk at Indiana University Executive AI Summit - 2020.

Guest Lecture on "Trajectory Optimization for UAVs", ENGR-599, Indiana University, 2019.

"Formation Control and Navigation of a Quadrotor Swarm" - ICUAS 2019.

Professional Service —

Reviewer

International Journal of Robust and Nonlinear Control

International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)

International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems(IROS)

IEEE Transaction on Robotics (T-RO)

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

International Symposium on Multi-Robot and Multi-Agent Systems (MRS)

Learning for Control and Dynamics Conference (L4DC)

Mentor

Undergraduate Research Opportunities in Computing (UROC) Program

Ben Siefers - Neural Network based Autonomous UAV Navigation	2020

Eric Tatman - Simulating UAV Swarm Dynamics 2020

Zach Seliger - Trajectory Generation and Control of a Crazyflie Drone 2018

Volunteering and Leadership -

IEEE Indiana University Student Branch

Founder, Vice Chair 2022/23

IEEE Region 4 (Midwest) Student Activity Committee (SAC) Responsibilities: Evaluating regional student activity award applications.

IEEE Region 10 (Asia/Pacific) Student Activity Committee (SAC)

Responsibilities: Evaluating regional student branch activity proposals and allocate funds.

IEEE Sri Lanka Section Executive Committee

Section Student Representative

Responsibilities: Coordinating the activities of student branches,

Promoting IEEE activities in Sri Lankan universities. 2015/16

Highlights: Membership numbers increased by 30% during my tenure.

IEEE Region 10 Student/Young Professional/Women in Engineering Congress

Core Organizer, 2015

Responsibilities: Leading the promotional activities team.

Highlights: The congress attracted 200+ foreign student delegates across the region.

IEEE University of Moratuwa Student Branch

Highlights: The student branch won two IEEE Darrel Chong Awards.

Vice Chair, 2013/14

Awards -

Luddy Travel Award, Indiana University

2022

2016

Graduate Student Fellowship, Indiana University

2017 - 2022

United Nations Development Program (UNDP) Hackathon - Sri Lanka

2016, Second Place

Google Summer of Code

For contributing to Mozilla Thunderbird's Calendar protocol for updating it to the latest RFC

2014, Mozilla

standards.

Institute of Engineers - Sri Lanka (IESL) Hackathon

2014, First Place

State Literary Competition (2009), Sri Lanka, Short Stories Division

2009, Finalist

References -

Prof. Martin Swany Chair, Dept. Intelligent Systems Engineering Indiana University Bloomington, IN, 47401

Prof. Ariful Azad
Dept. Intelligent Systems Engineering
Indiana University
Bloomington, IN, 47401

Dr. Ransalu Senanayake Dept. Computer Science Stanford University Stanford, CA, 94305

Prof. Minje Kim
Dept. Intelligent Systems Engineering
Indiana University
Bloomington, IN, 47401